Abraham: Cyber security is
extremely important especially
when it comes to sensitive data
And there are three main
types of sensitive data that
hackers tend to exploit?
These are Personal Information, Business
Information, and Classified information.
If these are accessed by cyber
criminals, it could be disastrous for
individuals, companies, organisations
and governments accordingly.
Nicole: Cyber-attacks can lead to the
illegal distribution of sensitive data
via the dark web, including personally
identifiable information [PII], protected
health information [PHI], personal
information, intellectual property,
or industry information systems.
It is extremely important that
sensitive data must always be
protected and inaccessible to all
who are not permitted to see it.
Restrictions on access of personal
or an organisation’s sensitive data,
needs to be robust especially when
it pertains to individual privacy and
property rights and even more so when
it involves areas of national security.
Abraham: Let’s have a
look at this more closely.
Sensitive data that includes
PII [Personally identifiable
information], PHI [Protected health
information] and personal information,
is held by many organisations.
It may be low level or high level and
should be kept secure accordingly.
Nicole: Personal Identifiable
Information [PII] is information
that can be used by a cybercriminal
to identify or locate an individual.
This could be a name, address, phone
numbers, data of birth, IP address,
location details, or any other
physical or digital identity data.
Think about how much of
this data is shared online
especially through social media.
Birthday details, age, phone number etc.
and then think about what could happen
if this data got into the wrong hands.
The less personal details and
information shown on social
media, the less PII information
is available to cyber criminals.
Abraham: Protected Health Information
[PHI] is [PII] that has been
collected through healthcare services.
This may relate to physical or mental
health of an individual, their access to
health care services, and any information
about their health status, including
medical histories, test results, mental
health information and even case studies.
PHI could be stolen by hackers
and sold or ransomed until the
healthcare organisation pays a fee
if they not adequately protected.
Nicole: Personal information in
the UK is covered by G.D.P.R.
and all personal data must be
processed securely using the
appropriate organisational measures.
To make sure this happens companies
must consider risk analysis regarding
the safety of data both physical
and digital, making sure that all
data is kept secure and encrypted.
Abraham: There are many kinds of
cyber security incidents but those
that involve personal data breaches
need to be reported to the ICO
[Information commissioners office]
within 72 hours of becoming aware of it.
If this affects an individual’s
rights and freedoms, then they
must also be told without delay.
Nicole: Where appropriate this will be
shared with the National Cyber security
centre [NCSC] and other law enforcement
and cyber crime agencies or regulators
such as NCA National Crime Agency [NCA],
the Financial Conduct Authority [FCA],
and the Payment Cards Industry [PCI].
Abraham: A key principle of the UK
General Data protection regulation
is that personal data is processed
securely and means that all systems
and services should have the correct
security to maintain confidentiality.
Nicole: Intellectual property is defined
as the creation of something, that
could be an invention, literary work,
artistic work, designs, symbols and images
that are used in everything around us,
including our websites and domain names.
The access, distribution of and
or use of without permission is
classed as intellectual property
crime and falls under cyber crime.
Intellectual property needs to be
protected by cyber security as when
private data is gained and sold
on, it can lead to counterfeiting,
database rights issues, trademark and
copyright misuse, impersonation etc.
Intellectual property usually belongs to
the author or creators of the asset, but
it belongs to an employer if the asset
is created whilst under their employment.
If a third party creates something
for another organisation the
intellectual property rights will
be with the third party but, the
responsibility for its safety will also
remain with the other organisation.
Abraham: There are two important pieces
of legislation concerning IP rights.
The Copyright Design and Patents Act
1988 [CDPA] deals with copyright,
including copyright in databases,
and defines what a database is.
The Copyright and Rights in
Databases Regulations 1997 [CRDR]
establishes what database rights are.
Nicole: Information systems
are present in most industries.
Finance and insurance, education,
Health services, Manufacturing,
Telecommunications, Data processing and
hosting and Government agencies of course.
Abraham: Common types of
information systems are ‘transaction
processing’, ‘management
information’, ‘decision-support’,
and ‘executive support’ systems.
Poor security in information
systems can leave an organisations
systems and services at risk.
It is therefore very important that
cyber security is in place at all levels.
Cyber security here involves personal
information in most cases and GDPR
compliance is a legal requirement.
Nicole: For further information
regarding this subject please check
out our other video links below.